Guide to the Louise Degn broadcast journalism audio-visual collection 1969-2007
Multimedia Archives, J. Willard Marriott Library, University of Utah
Louise Degn broadcast journalism audio-visual collection
1969-2007
University of Utah Libraries, Special Collections Audio Visual Archives Special Collections 295 South 1500 East Salt Lake City, Utah 84112-0860 (801) 581-8864
A0747
Degn, Louise
58 DVDs.
The Louise Degn broadcast journalism audio-visual collection (1969-2007) consists of news stories and documentaries reported or produced by Degn during her career as a television journalist, producer and documentary flmmaker. The majority of the material was filmed for local television stations in Salt Lake City, Utah. The collection also includes important broadcasts in the history of Utah and Utah broadcasting. Louise Degn is an award winning broadcast journalist and educator and a member of the Univeristy of Utah Communication Department faculty.
Biographical Note
Louise Degn graduated from Utah State University in 1968 with a degree in Political Science. In 1969, at the age of 23, Degn became only the second female broadcast reporter employed Salt Lake City's KSL Television. She graduated from Northwestern University in 1970 with a Master of Science in Journalism (MSJ).
In addition to her years as a reporter and at KSL (1969-1971, 1975-1982), Louise Degn worked as a news writer at Chicago's WBBM Television (1971-1973) and as an instructor at Brigham Young University (BYU) and news director of KBYU Television (1982) before returning to KSL as a producer in 1982.
In 1990 Degn left KSL to teach at the University of Utah, ultimately becoming an associate professor, associate department chair and undergraduate director in the Department of Communications.
The Louise Degn broadcast journalism audio-visual collection (1969-2007) consists of news stories and documentaries reported or produced by Degn during her career as a television journalist, producer and documentary flmmaker. The majority of the material was filmed for local television stations in Salt Lake City, Utah, and the bulk of these were reported for KSL-TV, where degn began her career as a reporter in 1969. Louise Degn is an award winning broadcast journalist and educator and a member of the Univeristy of Utah Communication Department faculty. DVDs contain completed versions and backgrounds of each news story and give an overall history of television news practices throughout the years. Original film and sounds elements exist for some segments.
This collection is arranged by subject. The initial arrangement of the records was prepared by the donor.
Materials must be used on-site; no use of original material, access copies will be made available for viewing. Five business days advanced notice required. Access to parts of this collection may be restricted under provisions of state or federal law, condition of the material, or by donor.
See also the Louise Degn photograph collection (P1160) and papers (Accn 2149).
Johnson, Sonia; KSL (Television Station: Salt Lake City, Utah); Salt Lake City (Utah); Great Salt Lake (Utah); Israel; Coalville (Utah); Television broadcasting of news--Utah; Equal rights amendments--United States; Arts, Humanities, and Social Sciences; Journalism; Material Types; Moving Images; Sound Recordings; Moving images; Sound recordings
- KSL-TV news stories - Louise Degn, reporter, 1969-1970; 2002; DVD (Disc 1)
  - About early TV news, 2002 June (Video 1)
    Television news production techniques 1969-1971. 09:27.
  - Zoo, 1969 September (Video 2)
    Animals get lonely in winter with fewer human visitors. 01:11.
    Louise Degn's note: This was my first TV news story. I interviewed Hogle Zoo director LaMar Farnsworth on the phone to get the facts, wrote the script, then went to the zoo with photographer Darius Gray to shoot it. I knew nothing about TV journalism as my emphasis in journalism school was newspaper journalism. Darius sat me down at a picnic table at the zoo and explained how TV news stories worked with A and B rolls. My voice sounds very amateurish as I'd had no voice training. Soon KSL hired Rex Campbell, a KSL radio legend, to give me voice lessons. Photographer/Editor: Darius Gray. Script available.
  - McKinley School 1-2, 1969 November 04 (Video 3)
    New behavior modification technique to treat children with autism. 02:20.
    Louise Degn's note: This story has natural sound of the classroom, which was a rare thing since there were only two sound cameras for the entire newsroom. Typical of news stories of this era, interviews are long. The parent story (Story 1) is 45 seconds long and the principal story (Story 2) is 37 seconds long. I'm not sure if the second story has been reconstructed correctly for this DVD since there was additional silent film left over. It is included under the "additional film" button. It shows a teacher employing a Behavior Modification technique to teach an autistic child to sit still and pay attention in class. Original scripts available.
  - McKinley School additional film, 1969 November 05 (Video 4)
    01:51.
  - Autumn, 1969 November 11 (Video 5)
    A feature story on autumn leaves. 01:11.
  - Thanksgiving Mass (audio only), 1969 November (Video 6)
    A Thanksgiving Mass at the Cathedral of the Madeleine. 01:33.
  - Christmas lights, 1969 December 01 (Video 7)
    Christmas lights downtown Salt Lake City. 01:08.
  - Bear Lake 1, 1969 December 02 (Video 8)
    New concerns about development, pollution, zoning around the lake. 01:32.
    Louise Degn's note: The environmental movement was part of the broader social changes that took place in the mid 1960s through the 1970s and was still in its early stages in 1969. Rural counties resisted placing governmnetal control over land yet were overwhelmed by the influx of growth. For these stories, I did research on the phone ahead of time. I shot the stories on a Bell and Howell silent camera over the course of two days. There are no interviews or stand-ups because spending that much time on a news story out of town was unusual and sending a second person with a camera was unthinkable. Photographer/Editor: Louise Degn. Original scripts available.
  - Bear Lake 2, 1969 December 03 (Video 9)
    01:45.
  - Old autos, 1969 December 04 (Video 10)
    Antique car collector, M. B. Held, in Farmington, Utah. 02:13.
    Louise Degn's note: In those days, I often travelled the back roads from Salt Lake to Ogden where my mother lived. Driving through Farmington, I'd always see a neat row of antique cars in a field located behind the house at 547 North Main, east of Lagoon. One day I stopped to investigate. The photographer on this story was Darius Gray. He shot the interview with an Airflex sound camera. The beginning uses old archival film of "horseless carriages" from a historic stock footage archive owned by KSL. I wanted to recreate that look for the ending of the story, so Darius used a Bolex silent camera, which has variable speed settings. He shot the scene in a slower speed so that when it was projected back at normal speed, it looks faster than normal. After three months on the job, this was the first story I did at KSL that I thought "worked". Photographer/Editor: Darius Gray. Original script available.
  - Salt Lake City streets, 1970 February 05 (Video 11)
    Street numbering system is off in Avenues and West Side. 01:18.
    Louise Degn's note: I'd lived in Salt Lake for five months in an apartment on 3rd Avenue. All my life I'd heard about Brigham Young's well-ordered street grid system and thought this anomaly in the numbering system was very odd. I shot the story with a Bell and Howell silent camera. In those days, the sound and picture were not edited together before the newscast but were mixed live on air (see Item 1 on this disc about Early TV News). Since this story has quick cuts, it was out-of-sync on the 6pm news. I was furious! At 10pm, however, they were more careful and got it right. In recreating these stories for DVD, I had the luxury of syncing sound and picture as close as possible. The original voice track was lost and has been rerecorded for this 2002 reconstruction. In 1972, the city of Salt Lake fixed the numbering problem by renaming First West as Second West, etc. The north streets were also renamed since they too were off-numbered. The Avenues numbering, however, was not changed. Photographer/Editor: Louise Degn. Original script available.
  - Family planning 1, 1970 March 04 (Video 12)
    Controversy over new publicly funded birth control clinics. 01:34.
    Louise Degn's note: The Birth Control Pill was introduced to the U.S. in 1960 and ushered in a social revolution regarding sexuality. The first publicly funded birth control clinic in Utah opened in 1968, so the social, medical and religious issues surrounding family planning were still new and controversial when this series ran in 1970. The prediction made in Story 1 that one day "houses and buildings will stretch from Ogden to Provo in one continuous super city" seemed far-fetched to many people in 1970, but proved to be true within 20-25 years. The stand-up in Story 1 is outside the Salt Lake County government complex at 21st South and State Street. The buildings, which formerly housed a county hospital, were torn down and replaced by a new government complex in 1986. Original scripts available.
  - Family planning 2, 1970 March 05 (Video 13)
    01:38.
  - Family planning 3, 1970 March 06 (Video 14)
    01:43.
  - Family planning 4, 1970 March 09 (Video 15)
    01:31.
  - Survival expedition 1, 1970 March 12 (Video 16)
    01:53.
  - Survival expedition 2, 1970 March 17 (Video 17)
  - Desert pack promo, 1970 June (Video 18)
    New wilderness survival technique to treat mentally ill patients. 01:11.
  - Roller coaster, 1970 March 24 (Video 19)
    Lagoon's roller coaster. 01:37.
  - Golden Eagle, 1970 June 12 (Video 20)
    New program to simplify national park fees. 01:50.
    Louise Degn's note: This story consists of one long stand-up, in two takes, without cue cards. Although stories in this era contained relatively few visuals, it is unusual that this story contained none. It was, I think, something we saw on the newswire and I ran out to do a quick story simply to have something to go on the air. Script available.
  - Women's liberation 1, 1970 June 29 (Video 21)
    The newly organized Utah Women's Liberation group in Utah. 01:56.
    Louise Degn's note: The Women's Movement began with the publication of The Feminine Mystique in 1963 by Betty Freidan. At that time, women could generally not open bank accounts or buy homes in their own name; they rarely had jobs other than as teachers, nurses or secretaries and most middle-class women quit their employment at the time of marriage. They rarely participated in vigorous sports nor challenged men in intellectual endeavors. The Women's Liberation Movement questioned assumptions about family, social and economic life and was controversial from the beginning. This series of stories attempted to explain the point of view of this new movement. Viewing these stories with 32 years hind-sight, I think they are very opinionated, advocating a point of view rather than reporting on a topic. Now, as a journalism teacher, I'd make a student of mine be more objective. The interview and stand-up in Story 1 were shot on sound film by Gene Minshall. The scenes of the nurse, secretary and telephone operator were shot on silent film. The sound of the telephone operators was recorded on audio tape and mixed later with the reporter narration. The stand-up was shot outside the Mountain Bell office on the northwest corner of 1st South and State Street.
  - Women's liberation 2, 1970 June 30 (Video 22)
    02:05.
    Louise Degn's note: Except for the stand-up at the beginning, this story was shot entirely on silent film and the interview was recorded on audio tape.
  - Women's liberation 3, 1970 July 01 (Video 23)
    01:58.
    Louise Degn's note: I shot the meeting at the Unitarian Church with a silent Bell and Howell camera (using the wrong f-stop, thus the film came out very dark.)
  - Women's liberation 4, 1970 July 03 (Video 24)
    Louise Degn's note: Stories 4-5 consist mainly of an interview, which was not too uncommon for news stories in 1970. Original scripts available.
  - Women's liberation 5, 1970 July 05 (Video 25)
    01:57.
  - Women's liberation 6, 1970 July 06 (Video 26)
  - Women's Liberation Day, 1970 August 26 (Video 27)
    50th anniversary of women's right to vote. 00:52.
    Louise Degn's note: Only remnants of flm of this story remains. See scripts for entire stories. Different versions for 6pm and 10pm newscasts. Original scripts available.
  - Phosphates 1, 1970 July 13 (Video 28)
    New environmental hazards of phosphates in laundry detergents. 01:04.
    Louise Degn's note: In 1970, it was still unusual for individuals to challenge a large corporation, like a soap manufacturer, and demand change in its products. The concept of "corporate citizenship" was unheard of. Original scripts available.
  - Phosphates 2, 1970 July 14 (Video 29)
    01:55.
  - Brigham Young cemetery, 1970 July 18 (Video 30)
    Brigham Young's grave site on 1st Avenue. 02:00.
    Louise Degn's note: I lived in the Avenues and walked to work at KSL, located at Social Hall Avenue between State Street and 2nd East. At that time, the lot east of the Brigham Young Cemetary was a vacant field and an old wooden staircase connected that field to a parking lot below on South Temple. I'd use the staircase on occassion and was fascinated to see the cemetary because even though I'd lived in Utah my entire life and was raised LDS, I'd never known about this place. I realized most Utahns also didn't know of it either and thought it would be interesting to do a little historical education piece on it. Note how the intersection of South Temple and Main Street looked before Main Street in front of the LDS temple was sold to the LDS church and closed to traffic in 1999. The original voice track for this story was lost and has been rerecorded for this 2002 reconstruction. Original script available.
  - Unit pricing, 1970 August 08 (Video 31)
    A new way to price items at the grocery store. 01:48.
    Louise Degn's note: Original script available.
  - Old Lyric Repertory Company, 1970 August 17 (Video 32)
    Acting company in Logan, Utah, performs in historic renovated theatre. 01:11.
    Louise Degn's note: I shot the story with a Bell and Howell silent camera. The original voice track was lost and has been rerecorded for this 2002 reconstruction. Original script available.
  - Shamrocks, 1970 August 23 (Video 33)
    Women's softball team in Utah. 01:16.
    Louise Degn's note: In the 1970s, few women participated in organized sports as highschools and colleges did not often have competitive inter-school leaugues for women. Sports also had separate rules for women; i.e. women could only pay half-court basketball. Overall, it was considered unfeminine for females to develop muscles and be too competitive. In this milieu, The Shamrocks were the only serious women's sports team in Utah. I once played basketball against them in a county recreation league and they trounced us. They were vastly superior to any other local team. In 1972, the federal government passed Title IX, a law requiring equal spending for men's and women's sport teams in the schools. Gradually, women gained greater opportunity and many competitve female athletes developed. Original script available.
  - Mental health, 1970 September 03 (Video 34)
    New community-based treatment for mental illness. 02:11.
    Louise Degn's note: The patient-rights movement, along with other social movements, was beginning to gain ground in the mid to late 1960s. In response to a federal law, states were closing down large, centralized hospitals which had warehoused mentally ill patients for years and moving them to smaller, community-based facilities. I am struck at the naivete of the statement in my stand-up, quoting Sue Motz, saying that a woman hospitalized for 24 years could soon return home simply because she's now being treated in a community facility. This illustrated the great hope people place in these new treatments. People could not have realized in 1970 that the under-funding of these community treatment centers and the tightening of federal commitment laws would contribute to the vast homeless problem that surfaced in the 1980s. One aspect of the patient-rights movement, though, had not yet materialized in 1970 as we were given free access to film the patients' faces without consent forms. The stand-up is outside the facility at the Salt Lake County government complex on 21st South and State Street. Original script available.
- KSL-TV news stories - Louise Degn, reporter, 1970-1971; 2002; DVD (Disc 2)
  - About early TV news, 2002 June (Video 1)
  - Mansion 1, 1970 September 21 (Video 2)
    The Colonel Enos Wall Mansion, 411 East South Temple. 01:56.
    Louise Degn's not: I asked two actors to dress up in "old-fashioned" formal attire to recreate the look of guests arriving at the mansion, riding the elevator, entering the ballroom, etc. only to see it transformed into the modern day (i.e. ugly) classroom. Several times during my career I tried to recreate scenes with actors; seldom did they work. The opening stand-up, original voice track and music were lost and the latter two have been rerecorded for this 2002 reconstruction. Original script available.
  - Mansion 2, 1970 September 22 (Video 3)
    The David Keith Mansion, 529 East South Temple. 02:12.
    Louise Degn's note: Terracor, the land-development company which occupied the mansion eventually went out of business. Their big poject, Stansbury Park (near Tooele) never took off and it took Tooele County another 30 years before it began to see large-scale growth. Unlike Devereaux and Wall, the Keith Mansion had been used as a home until the previous year. I talked to the home's last resident on the telephone. She was very helpful in telling me about the mansion but when asked why she sold it, she became disconcerted. Apparently, in polite society, one does not ask such things. The closing production elements are missing in this story. It should turn to black and white, freeze and old-fashioned scroll-work should frame the people to make it look like a photograph from the 1900 time period. Original script available.
  - Mansion 3, 1970 September 23 (Video 4)
    The Devereaux House, 334 West South Temple. 02:12.
    Louise Degn's note: This mansion fascinated me the most of all three. I could see the elegance underneath the wreck and thought it would never have the chance at revival since it was in an industrial part of the city. Little did I realize that the western part of downtown Salt Lake City would soon become as valuable as the eastern part. The mansion was included on the National Register of Historic Places in March of 1971, six months after this story aired. In 1979, the State of Utah purchased the building. It was renovated and turned into a restuarant as part of the Triad Center development in 1984-1985. Original script available.
  - Sesame Street (audio only), 1970 October 09 (Video 5)
    Children's show on public television begins its 2nd year. 01:58.
  - Sesame Street Roosevelt Franklin song (audio only), 1970 October 09 (Video 6)
    02:31.
  - Nutcracker, 1970 December (Video 7)
    Profile of Ballet West wardrobe mistress. 02:28.
    Louise Degn's note: The film from the first part of the story is lost.
  - Salvation Army story, 1970 December (Video 8)
    A description of the Salvation Army religion. 02:02.
    Louise Degn's note: Like most people, I did not realize that the Salvation Army was a religion. I learned that fact reading a story in a Chicago newspaper during my graduate days at Northwestern University. The original voice track of this story was lost and has been rerecorded for this 2002 reconstruction. Original handwritten script and typescript are both available.
  - Salvation Army additional film, 1970 December (Video 9)
    02:04.
  - Student tutor, 1971 January 24 (Video 10)
    Students teach other students in Weber School District. 02:13.
    Louise Degn's note: The original voice track of this story was lost and has been rerecorded for this 2002 reconstruction. Original script available.
  - Coalville Tabernacle 1 story, 1971 February 14 (Video 11)
    History of LDS pioneer tabernacle to be torn down. 01:30.
    Louise Degn's note: I love old buildings. In fact, I quit KSL in Septmebr of 1980 to study restoration architecture for 18 months, so when I was alerted to the story by a newspaper article, I was eager to do a feature story and get a first-hand look at the Coalville Tabernacle. Five days later, the story erupted with public demonstrations and a legal challenge. It was the first time, I recall, that the LDS church was challenged publicly in this way by its own members. The prevailing ethic of the time was to tear old buildings down and build modern ones. Coalville was not the only tabernacle torn down. Utah restoration architect Alan Roberts made an inventory in 1974 of pioneer Mormon tabernacles and found that of 43 buildings, 22 had been demolished and 21 remained, most of which had been renovated. It seems that this story was an example of the LDS church not knowing how to handle public relations. The Church saw its communication lines as moving through Priesthood channels rather than through the public media. Criticism was thought of as "challenging truth" and leaders had little experience answering questions in a public forum. The next LDS church president, Spencer W. Kimball, tried to extend himself to the media, though he was never comfortable doing so. The LDS church truly mastered public relations under President Gordon B. Hinkley during the 2002 Winter Olympics in Salt Lake City. For further reading, see Dialogue: A Journal of Mormon Thought, Vol. V, No. 4/Winter 1970. I wrote the second of the three articles as "Anonymous" as I was still employed at KSL at the time. Original script available.
  - Coalville Tabernacle 1 additional film, 1971 February 14 (Video 12)
  - Coalville Tabernacle 2 story, 1971 February 19 (Video 13)
    Court stops demolition. Public demonstrations against LDS Church. 02:08.
  - Coalville Tabernacle 2 additional film, 1971 February 19 (Video 14)
    00:39.
  - Coalville Tabernacle 3 story, 1971 March 01 (Video 15)
    Court lifts stay, allowing demolition. 01:43.
  - Coalville Tabernacle 3 additional film, 1971 March 01 (Video 16)
    Court hearing, stake president interview. 01:50.
  - Coalville Tabernacle 3 additional film, 1971 March 01 (Video 17)
    Court hearing, attorney interview. 02:00.
  - Coalville Tabernacle 4 story, 1971 March 03 (Video 18)
    Coalville church members begin demolition of tabernacle. 03:03.